A Guide to the Robert S. Gamble Manuscript Collection on Sully: The Biography of a House, 1961-1978
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Robert S. Gamble Manuscript Collection on Sully: The Biography of a House, 1961-1978
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 08-06
4.0 linear feet
The Robert S. Gamble Manuscript Collection on Sully: The Biography of a House consists of 4.0 linear feet and spans the years 1961-1978, containing Gamble’s original research papers, research notecards, correspondence, notes, photocopies, newspaper clippings, photographs and negatives, relating to his 1973 book about Sully Plantation.
Gamble, Robert S. (1943-)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
The collection has a complicated history. The bulk of the collection was donated to Fairfax County Public Library by Robert S. Gamble throughout 1976-1977 without a deed of gift. The photographs used for the book were removed from the collection and incorporated into the Virginia Room’s “Photographic Archive of Fairfax County, Virginia”. Two boxes of Gamble’s research notecards were transferred to the Fairfax County Park Authority. It also appears additional files may have been added to the collection by staff from the Virginia Room and the Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning. In December 2016, Mr. Gamble retroactively signed a deed of gift officially donating his collection to FCPL. In February 2018, Gamble’s research notecards were returned to FCPL by the Park Authority. In May 2018, the research notecards and photographs were reunited with the collection, and it now exists as originally donated.
Historical and Biographical Information
In 1971, the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors expressed a desire to publish a study on the history of Sully Plantation. Henry Lee I purchased Sully in 1725, and it later passed down to his grandson, Richard Bland Lee, who built the house in 1794. Several families lived on the plantation until the Fairfax County Park Authority acquired the site in 1959, saving it from demolition during the construction of Dulles International Airport. The Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning appointed Robert S. Gamble to prepare a study that would be published as a booklet.
The booklet unexpectedly grew into a book because of the wealth of records Gamble uncovered that revealed how Sully played a more important role in Fairfax County’s history than anyone had previously realized. The Sully Foundation, a non-profit organization established by Robert E. “Eddie” Wagstaff in 1969 to promote and support the preservation and interpretation of the Sully Historic Site, supported and underwrote the book’s publication. The Foundation published Gamble’s book, “Sully: The Biography of a House” in 1973, and it is widely regarded as the definitive study on Sully Plantation. The book received an award of Merit from the American Association for State and Local History in 1974, as an exemplary study of its kind. The book has since gone through several printings.
Robert Scott Gamble was born in Huntsville, Alabama on August 24, 1943. He graduated from Gadsden High School in 1961, received a B.A. in History and Political Science from Birmingham Southern College in 1965, and an M.A. in History from the University of Georgia in 1967.
After graduating, Gamble served in the Peace Corps and worked in the National Preservation Office of Dominican Republic. In 1969, he joined the staff of the National Park Service, working with the National Register of Historic Places, and later the National Survey of Historic Sites and Buildings. Gamble also worked as an historian for the Advisory Council of Historic Preservation and in 1982, he became the senior architectural historian for the Alabama Historical Commission.
In 1989, the Society of Architectural Historians awarded Gamble the Antoinette Forrester Downing Award for his book, The Alabama Catalog: Historic American Buildings Survey: A Guide to the Early Architecture of the State, which detailed the history of architecture in Alabama and reviewed the state’s properties surveyed by the Historic American Buildings Survey.
Scope and Content
The Robert S. Gamble Manuscript Collection on Sully: The Biography of a House consists of 4.0 linear feet and spans the years 1961-1978, containing Gamble’s original research papers, research notecards, correspondence, notes, photocopies, newspaper clippings, photographs and negatives, relating to his 1973 book about Sully Plantation.
Series 1: Research Files, 1961-1976, Boxes 1-6
This series contains the files gathered over the course of Robert Gamble’s research in 1971-1973 for the book Sully: The Biography of a House. The files consist of research notecards, correspondence, notes, photocopies, newspaper clippings, and other papers used by Gamble for his research. Boxes 4 and 5 consist of research notecards that contain excerpts from primary documents including data not actually used in the book. A few files appear to have come from the Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning: the Robert S. Gamble speeches, notes, etc folder in Box 1 and the correspondence files in Box 3. Correspondence found throughout the collection includes letters from Robert S. Gamble, Eleanor Lee Templeman, Bayard D. Evans, Nan Netherton, John Porter Bloom, John K. Gott, Robert W. Jentsch, Walter M. Macomber, Vernon W. Barlow, Martha Barlow, and many others whom Gamble and the Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning staff corresponded with during research for the book.
Series 2: Photographs and Graphics, Undated, Box 7
These are the original photographs, graphics, and negatives that Gamble used in his book Sully: The Biography of a House. The photographs in this series are not a complete set of the images used in the final published book. Photographs are organized by page number as they appeared in the book.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
Index Terms
Barlow, Martha Estelle (1908-1976); Barlow, Vernon Westphal (1906-1986); Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning; Gamble, Robert S. (1943-); Historic buildings -- Virginia-- Fairfax County; Plantations -- Virginia -- Fairfax County; The Society of the Lees of Virginia; Sully Foundation, Inc.; Sully Plantation (Fairfax County, Va.); Templeman, Eleanor Lee (1906-1990); Wagstaff, Robert Edward (1897-1970)
Container List
- Series 1: Research Files, 1961-1976
  - Sully Brochures and Programs, 1965-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Robert S. Gamble speeches, notes, etc [files appears to have come from Office of Comprehensive Planning], 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gamble, Robert S. Sully. August 1971. Preliminary Draft, 1971 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gamble, Robert S. Sully: An Historical and Architectural Report. Outline submitted February 12, 1971., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Grigg, Wood, Browne, and Williams, architects. Sully Plantation: A Feasibility Study for Preservation Prepared for the Fairfax County Park Authority. December 5, 1973., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Resumes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Original Manuscripts (Photocopies of Alexander Haight papers), Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Research notes, Chapter 1, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Research notes, Chapter 2, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Research notes, Chapter 3, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Research notes, Chapter 4 - Moidone Papers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Research notes, Chapter 4, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Research notes, Chapter 4 - Francis L. Lee Committees and Inventories., Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Research notes, Chapter 5, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Research notes, Chapter 6, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Research notes, Chapter 7, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Research notes, Chapter 7 - Miller Family, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Research notes, Chapter 7 - Shear Family, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Research notes, Chapter 8, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Research notes, Furniture, 1963-1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Research notes, Turberville Letters, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Research notes, Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Maps and Illustrations, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1971, 1961-1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1978, 1972-1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sully Foundation, Ltd. Annual Report, 1971, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Outline History of Sully (manual prepared for docents of Sully), Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Research notecards, Chapters 1-3, Undated (Box 4)
  - Research notecards, Chapters 4-9, Personal Tax, and Land Tax Records, Undated (Box 5)
  - Hardcover preliminary draft, 1971 August (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Final edited manuscript, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Photographs and Graphics, Undated
  - SULLY, P. 002a - Richard Lee of Machodoc, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 002b - 1725 land patent, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 004 - 1725 survey, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 007 - Thomas Lee of Stratford, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 008a - Henry Lee I of "Lee Hall", portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 008b - Mary Bland Lee of "Lee Hall", portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 010 - Robert "King" Carter, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 016 - Richard Bland Lee, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 020 - Richard Bland Lee's 1787 advertisement, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 025 - Alexander Hamilton, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 029a - Battle of Bunker's Hill. Painting by John Trumbull. Yale University Art Gallery, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 029b - "The Death of General Montgomery in the Attack on Quebec", Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 036 - Richard Bland Lee, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 037 - Elizabeth Collins Lee, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 43 - Thomas Lee Shippen of Philadelphia, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 45 - Pencil sketch of Cornelia Lee, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 46a - William Hodgson, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 46b - Portia Lee, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 047 - Coachee from Philadelphia, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 048 - Fire Insurance policies taken out by Richard Bland Lee in 1801 and 1805, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 049 - 1801 Alexandria Gazette advertisement for Sully [photo not used in the final manuscript], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 053a - Strawberry Vale, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 053b - Washington residence of Richard Bland Lee, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 054a - Locket with strand of George Washington's hair [and negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 054b - Congressional cemetery. Richard Bland Lee's grave, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 056 - Richard Henry Lee, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 060 - 1816 advertisement for the sale of Sully, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 063 - 1825 Daily Intelligencer advertisement for the Sully boys academy, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 065 - Henry Tazewell Harrison of Leesburg, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 066 - 1835 letter, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 068 - John A. Robertson documents, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 072 - Christ Church cemetary, Alexandria, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 074a -1842 advertisement for Sully in the "Alexandria Gazette", Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 074b - Jacob Haight, portrait (retouched), Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 074b - Jacob Haight, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 075a - Amy Haight, portrait (retouched), Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 075a - Amy Haight, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 075b - Dutchess County, New York, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 077 - Plat of Sully drawn in 1843, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 081 - Samuel Janney, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 082a - Alexander Haight, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 082b - Phebe Haight, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 082b - Phebe Haight, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 083a - James Haight Barlow, portrait (retouched), Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 083a - James Haight Barlow, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 083b - Maria Haight Barlow, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 084 - "Little Sully," built 1840s. Burned 1969, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 084 - "Little Sully," built 1840s. Burned 1969, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 087 - Plat of Sully, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 088 - Jacob Haight Barlow, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 088 - Jacob Haight Barlow, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 093 - Adm. Samuel Phillips Lee, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 094 - P.G.T. Beauregard, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 095 - Confederate trenches at Centreville, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 096 - McDowell may of Sully area, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 097 - Jacob Haight Barlow, portrait (retouched), Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 097 - Jacob Haight Barlow, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 099 - Manassas Junction after Stonewall Jackson's raid, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 102 - Fairfax Courthouse during the Civil War, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 105 - Cleo, the Haight's servant girl, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 107a - Fitzhugh Lee, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 107b - Wade Hampton, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 107c - J.E.B. Stuart, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 110 - Colonel John Singleton Mosby, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 116 - Lt. Richard Titus, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 117a - Nettie Barlow, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 117b - Jacob Barlow, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 118 - Stephen Shear, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 119 - Gertrude Shear, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 120a - Conrad Shear, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 120a - Conrad Shear, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 120b - Anna Eliza Shear, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 120b - Anna Eliza Shear, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 121 - Abraham Lincoln lithograph, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 122 - Lillie Shear and Addie Shear c.1875, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 123 - Hopkins map showing Sully area, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 125a - George and Ellen Currie, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 125a - George and Ellen Currie, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 125b - George Currie, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 126 - Sully in the early 1900s, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 126 - Sully in the early 1900s, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 127 - William Eads Miller, Sully's owner from 1911 to 1919, portrait (retouched), Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 127 - William Eads Miller, Sully's owner from 1911 to 1919, portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 128 - Sully, winter 1912, Mrs. Gilbert McLearen, Mrs. J.A. Seaton, Mr. Gilbert McLearen, Mr. George William Smith, and Ralph Rose [and negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 128 - Sully, winter 1912, Mrs. Gilbert McLearen, Mrs. J.A. Seaton, Mr. Gilbert McLearen, Mr. George William Smith, and Ralph Rose, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 129 - Harris girls at Sully, daughters of Jeff Harris, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 129 - Harris girls at Sully, daughters of Jeff Harris, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 130a - King and Rebecca Poston seated on the steps of the south porch, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 130a - King and Rebecca Poston seated on the steps of the south porch, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 130b - View of Sully, 1939, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 131 - Ambassador Walter Thurston and mother Beatrice Thurston, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 132 - Frederick E. Nolting Jr., portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 134 - Leeton (at Dulles), Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 135 - "Northern Virginia Sun" headline, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 137 - Sully, view from SE, summer 1960 [and negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 137 - Sully, view from SE, summer 1960, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 137 - Sully, view from SE, summer 1960, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 138 - R.E. Wagstaff, curator of Sully, standing before the north side of the house, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 139 - Gov. Mills Godwin and R.E. Wagstaff at Sully, 1966, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 140a - Art exhibition on the Sully grounds, 1968, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 140b - Dulles International Airport's soaring terminal building, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 147 - The "Salisbury Plain run" tract--3311 acres of virgin land lying between Cub ("Salisbury Plain") and Bull run, Undated
  - SULLY, P. 148 - Map of Sully estate, about 1805, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 148 - Compass rose and scale overlay for maps on pp. 148-152. [overlay], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 149 - Map of Sully estate, about 1860, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 150 - Map of Sully estate, about 1890, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 151 - Map of Sully estate, about 1940, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 152 - Map of Sully estate, in 1970s, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 153 - HABS site plan for Sully [oversize negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 153 - HABS site plan for Sully, Undated
  - SULLY, P. 154 - Site plan, 1973, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 155 - Possibly earliest known photo of Sully, ice house and outbuildings, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 156 - Sully Plantation, Chantilly, Va. North view of mansion house, 1936 HABS [3 photos and negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 159 - Sully, South elevation. Measured drawing [and negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 159 - Sully, South elevation. Measured drawing, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 159 - Sully, South elevation. Measured drawing, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 159 - Sully, South elevation. Measured drawing [oversize negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 160 - Floor plan, first floor [oversize negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 161 - Floor plan, second floor [oversize negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 162 - Floor plan, third floor [oversize negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 164 - Sully, South porch detail, 1936 HABS, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 165 - Sully, Brick nogging, 1936 HABS, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 169 - Entrance hall and staircase [and negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 169 - Entrance hall and staircase, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 173 - East wing breakfront, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 179 - Third floor bedchamber, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 180a - Mantelpiece in dining room, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 180b - From Batty Langley, "Treasury", Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 1821 - From Abraham Swan, "Designs in Carpentry", Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 182a - Dropleaf Pembroke table (Hepplewhite, ca. 1790-1800). Owned by Mrs. Eleanor Lee Templeman [and negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 182c - Hepplewhite card table, c. 1790 [and negative], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 185 - Detached kitchen built in 1794, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 188a - The dairy building in 1939, showing the crude second-story enclosed porch on the south end, and a dilapidated lean-to, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 188a - The dairy building in 1939, showing the crude second-story enclosed porch on the south end, and a dilapidated lean-to, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 188b - Stone dairy building and residence, 1961, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 189 - Dairy, smokehouse and kitchen, 1971, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 191 - Smokehouse, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 193 - Schoolhouse, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 197 - Log bridge built c. 1846-50 [and negatives], Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 197 - Log bridge built c. 1846-50 (contact sheet), Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 197 - Log bridge built c. 1846-50 (contact sheet), Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 198 - "Little Sully", Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 199 - Barns at "Little Sully", Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 199 - Barns at "Little Sully", Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 200a - Cutaway view of 1849 barn, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 200a - Cutaway view of 1849 barn, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 200b - Cutaway view of Hudson Valley barn, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 200b - Cutaway view of Hudson Valley barn, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 200c - Cutaway view of 1871 barn, Undated (Box 7)
  - SULLY, P. 200c - Cutaway view of 1871 barn, Undated (Box 7)